ibc.ca 2016-11-03

# Privacy

**PRINCIPLE 1: ACCOUNTABILITY**  
IBC is responsible for the personal information under its control. The IBC Chief Privacy Officer is accountable for the organization’s compliance with the principles set out in this document and all applicable provincial and federal privacy legislation. 

**PRINCIPLE 2: IDENTIFYING PURPOSES**  
The purposes for which personal information is collected shall be identified by IBC at or before the time the information is collected.

  1. IBC shall document the purposes for which personal information is collected. Identifying the purposes for which personal information is collected at or before the time of collection allows IBC to determine the information it needs to collect to fulfill these purposes. 
  2. When personal information that has been collected is to be used for a purpose not previously identified, the new purpose shall be identified prior to use. Unless the new purpose is permitted by law, the consent of the individual is required before information can be used for that purpose.

 **PRINCIPLE 3: CONSENT**  
The knowledge and consent of the individual are generally required for the collection, use, or disclosure of personal information. In most cases, IBC must rely on consent obtained by insurance companies. 

  1. Consent is generally required for the collection of personal information and the subsequent use or disclosure of this information. In certain circumstances, consent with respect to use or disclosure may be sought after the information has been collected but before use (for example, to use information for a purpose not previously identified).
  2. The principle requires “knowledge and consent’’. In the limited cases where IBC collects information directly from the individual, IBC shall ensure that the individual is advised of the purposes for which the information will be collected, used and disclosed.
  3. IBC shall not, as a condition of the supply of a product or service, require an individual to consent to the collection, use, or disclosure of information beyond that required to fulfill the explicitly specified and legitimate purposes.
  4. The method for obtaining consent may vary depending on the circumstances and the type of information collected. IBC will generally seek express consent when the information is likely to be considered sensitive. Implied consent would generally be appropriate when the information is less sensitive.
  5. An individual may withdraw consent at any time, subject to legal or contractual restrictions and reasonable notice. In that event, the individual will be informed of the consequences of such withdrawal.
  6. Note: In certain circumstances personal information can be collected, used, or disclosed without the knowledge and consent of the individual. An example is information collected for the detection and prevention of fraud or for law enforcement, for which seeking the consent of the individual might defeat the purpose of collecting the information.

 **PRINCIPLE 4: LIMITING COLLECTION**  
The collection of personal information shall be limited to that which is necessary for the purposes identified by IBC. Information shall be collected by fair and lawful means.

  1. Personal information shall not be collected indiscriminately. Both the amount and the type of information collected shall be limited to that which is necessary to fulfill the purposes identified.

 **PRINCIPLE 5: LIMITING USE, DISCLOSURE, AND RETENTION**  
Personal information shall not be used or disclosed for purposes other than those for which it was collected, except with the consent of the individual or as allowed or required by law. Personal information shall be retained only as long as necessary for the fulfillment of those purposes. 

  1. Where personal information is used for a new purpose, IBC shall document this purpose. A full Privacy Impact Assessment must be undertaken.
  2. In developing retention cycles, IBC shall consider both the requirements of the business and any applicable IBC corporate standards. In addition, retention cycles may be subject to legislative requirements.
  3. Upon reaching its expiry date, personal information files and/or records will be destroyed, erased, or rendered anonymous. Computerized files are purged through automated system provisions. Manual repositories are usually purged through controlled and secure destruction of the records, e.g., shredding.
  4. If IBC discloses information to third parties, it must track all distributions of the information. That is, who received what, when, and why, as needed.

 **PRINCIPLE 6: ACCURACY**  
Personal information shall be as accurate, complete, and up to date as is necessary for the purposes for which it is  
to be used. 

  1. Information shall be sufficiently accurate, complete, and up to date to minimize the possibility that inappropriate information may be used to make a decision about the individual.
  2. Personal information that is used on an ongoing basis, including information that is disclosed to third parties, should generally be accurate and up to date, unless limits to the requirement for accuracy are clearly set out.

 **PRINCIPLE 7: SAFEGUARDS**  
Personal information shall be protected by security safeguards appropriate to the sensitivity of the information.

  1. The security safeguards shall protect information against loss or theft, as well as unauthorized access, disclosure, copying, use, or modification. This requirement applies to personal information regardless of the format in which it is held.
  2. The nature of the safeguards will vary depending on the sensitivity of the information that has been collected, the amount, distribution, and format of the information, and the method of storage.
  3. Care shall be used in the disposal or destruction of personal information, in order to prevent unauthorized parties from gaining access to the information.

 **PRINCIPLE 8: OPENNESS**  
IBC shall make readily available to individuals specific information about its policies and practices relating to the management of personal information. 

  1. Individuals shall be able to acquire information about IBC’s privacy policies and practices without unreasonable effort. This information shall be made available in a form that is generally understandable.

 **PRINCIPLE 9: INDIVIDUAL ACCESS**  
Upon request and where practical, an individual shall be informed of the existence, use, and disclosure of his/her personal information and shall be given access to that information. An individual shall be able to challenge the accuracy and completeness of the information and have it amended as appropriate. These provisions are to be applied with due regard for IBC’s obligations to its members.

  1. Where IBC data stores are the primary or originating source of a particular set of personal information, IBC will develop the capability required to address the following:
    1. Provide individual access to that information, including:
      * A record search and find capability.
      * Data contents display (printout).
    2. If the information is challenged, the record must be flagged and the challenge indicated in any subsequent use or disclosure of the information. 
    3. If the information is challenged successfully, the contents must be corrected.
    4. If the requested change is denied and the individual pursues the matter (appeals), the record must be flagged as “under dispute” and so reported in any subsequent disclosure.
    5. Upon final resolution, the contents should be set as “decided” and the flag removed.
  2. The requested information shall be provided or made available in a form that is generally understandable. For example, if abbreviations or codes are used to record information, an explanation shall be provided.
  3. IBC will provide access to an individual’s personal information records. However, there could be some limitations to our ability to respond to requests.
    * Some of the information may not be organized in a manner that makes personal information accessible.
    * In providing the information, we may delete portions that disclose personal information about other individuals.
    * If individuals have concerns with the accuracy of the information, IBC will inform them of the organization that had sent the data so that the individual can request a correction from the source of the information. In many cases, IBC merely has custody, not ownership of the information.
  4. IBC will provide an account of the use that has been made or is being made of personal information and to whom it has been disclosed. When it is not possible to provide a list of the organizations to which it has actually disclosed information about an individual, IBC will provide a list of organizations to which it may have disclosed information about the individual.
  5. When an individual successfully demonstrates to IBC’s source of the information, the inaccuracy or incompleteness of personal information, IBC will amend the information as requested by the source.
  6. When a challenge is not resolved to the satisfaction of the individual, the substance of the unresolved challenge shall be recorded. Where appropriate, the amended information or the existence of the unresolved challenge shall be transmitted to third parties having access to the information in question.

 **PRINCIPLE 10: CHALLENGING COMPLIANCE**  
An individual shall be able to address a challenge concerning compliance with the foregoing principles to the IBC Chief Privacy Officer.

  1. Procedures are in place to receive and respond to complaints or inquiries about IBC policies and practices relating to the handling of personal information. The complaint procedures are easily accessible and simple to use.
  2. IBC will investigate all complaints. If a complaint is found to be justified, IBC will take appropriate measures including, if necessary, amending its policies.

 **Requests for access to personal information and further information on our privacy policy are to be sent to:**

 **Chief Privacy Officer**  
Insurance Bureau of Canada  
777 Bay Street, Suite 2400  
Toronto, Ontario  
M5G 2C8  
Fax: (416) 644-4965  
Email: [cpo@ibc.ca](mailto:cpo@ibc.ca)
